<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Section xmlns="urn:com.io7m.structural:8:0"
         id="cb46abcd-d0b1-41f4-bb95-662186d4aa78"
         title="Windows">

  <Section title="Description">
    <Subsection title="Overview">
      <FormalItem title="Windows">
        <Image source="window.png"
               width="640"
               height="268">
          Two example windows.
        </Image>
      </FormalItem>

      <Paragraph>
        A <Term type="term">window</Term> is an interactive, resizable, rectangular region that acts as a container for <Link target="0c480fad-ee66-4532-a0b1-f06ebe582ea8">
        components</Link>.
      </Paragraph>
    </Subsection>

    <Subsection title="Window Order"
                id="caab0ac3-f623-457f-986d-312b260f184e">
      <Paragraph>
        Each window is assigned an abstract <Term type="term">order</Term> value by the screen in which it resides. The
        order encodes the notion of windows being in a stack, with the window at the top of the stack being the
        frontmost or <Term type="term">focused</Term> window. When the user clicks on any component within a window,
        that window is moved to the top of the stack and becomes <Term type="term">focused</Term>.
      </Paragraph>
    </Subsection>

    <Subsection title="Window Visibility">
      <Paragraph>
        Windows are either <Term type="term">visible</Term>, or <Term type="term">invisible</Term>. An invisible window
        is not rendered, and does not receive
        <Link target="bcc3c7a6-df1c-4dc8-8263-2364630db64a">events</Link>.
      </Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>
        When a window's visibility changes,
        <Link target="bcc3c7a6-df1c-4dc8-8263-2364630db64a">events</Link>
        of type
        <Term type="type">SyWindowBecameInvisible</Term>
        or
        <Term type="type">SyWindowBecameVisible</Term>
        will be published.
      </Paragraph>
    </Subsection>

    <Subsection title="Window Layers">
      <Paragraph>
        Windows can be grouped into <Term type="term">layers</Term>. A layer is an integer value
        <Term type="variable">N</Term>
        such that all windows with a layer value less than
        <Term type="variable">N</Term>
        are considered to be <Term type="term">below</Term> windows with layer value <Term type="variable">N</Term>. All
        windows with a layer value greater than <Term type="variable">N</Term> are considered to be
        <Term type="term">above</Term>
        windows with layer value <Term type="variable">N</Term>.
      </Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>
        Within an individual layer, <Link target="caab0ac3-f623-457f-986d-312b260f184e">window order</Link> decides
        which windows are above or below other windows in that layer.
      </Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>
        Window layers are a somewhat advanced feature, and most applications will not need to use them directly. They
        are primarily useful for implementing UI elements that must temporarily appear above all other elements, such as
        notifications or <Link target="ddd1079c-f636-4232-bebe-39672a140061">menus</Link>. They are also useful for
        implementing user interfaces for games and other simulations; the game's HUD can be placed on one layer, and a
        "pause" screen UI can be placed on a separate layer above the HUD layer, and the layers can individually be
        shown or hidden as is appropriate.
      </Paragraph>
    </Subsection>

    <Subsection title="Snapping">
      <Paragraph>
        The positions and sizes of windows can be configured to <Term type="term">snap</Term> to given values. For
        example, if a window's <Term type="expression">positionSnapping</Term> attribute is set to
        <Term type="constant">16</Term>, whenever the position of a window is set (either manually, or via the user
        dragging the window), the position on both axes will snap to the nearest multiple of
        <Term type="constant">16</Term>.
      </Paragraph>
    </Subsection>
  </Section>

  <Section title="Window Decorations">
    <Subsection title="Standard Components">
      <Paragraph>
        Windows are created with a standard set of attached components. These standard components allow users to perform
        actions such as closing windows, maximizing windows, and moving and resizing windows. Whether these components
        are visible or not is dependent upon both the window's
        <Link target="6aeefd35-8837-4503-99ee-3ccba984a49e">theme</Link>, and other per-window configuration settings.
        By default, the standard components are visible if the window is configured as being
        <Term type="term">decorated</Term>.
      </Paragraph>
      <FormalItem title="Decorated Window">
        <Image source="window_parts.png"
               width="640"
               height="344">
          A decorated window.
        </Image>
      </FormalItem>
      <Paragraph>
        As an example, the window shown in the above diagram appears as follows when marked as
        <Term type="term">undecorated</Term>:
      </Paragraph>
      <FormalItem title="Undecorated Window">
        <Image source="window_undecorated.png"
               width="640"
               height="462">
          A decorated window.
        </Image>
      </FormalItem>
      <Paragraph>
        Windows can be switched between being <Term type="term">decorated</Term> or
        <Term type="term">undecorated</Term>
        at any time by setting the value of the
        <Term type="variable">decorated</Term>
        attribute. Note that, without window decorations, the user has very little control over the window: They cannot
        directly close it, move it, or resize it.
      </Paragraph>
    </Subsection>

    <Subsection title="Close Button">
      <Subsection title="Description">
        <Paragraph>
          The <Term type="term">close</Term> button, when clicked, closes the window. The button is a
          <Link target="9c6bfe16-d2dd-420b-b8ba-9d087bb9091c">standard button</Link>
          and therefore follows the same behaviours with respect to keyboard and mouse interaction.
        </Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>
          For a visible window, the close button is visible iff the following conditions hold:
        </Paragraph>
        <FormalItem title="Visibility Conditions">
          <ListUnordered>
            <Item>
              The window is decorated.
            </Item>
            <Item>
              The window's <Term type="variable">closeButtonVisibility</Term> attribute is set to
              <Term type="constant">VISIBILITY_VISIBLE</Term>.
            </Item>
          </ListUnordered>
        </FormalItem>
      </Subsection>
      <Subsection title="Events" id="29c70488-7d76-4091-9f7e-c6d4a6c66476">
        <Paragraph>
          When a window is closed, an event of type <Term type="type">SyWindowClosed</Term> will be published.
        </Paragraph>
      </Subsection>
    </Subsection>

    <Subsection title="Maximize Button">
      <Subsection title="Description">
        <Paragraph>
          The <Term type="term">maximize</Term> button, when clicked, resizes the window to match the size of the
          screen's <Link target="f390c685-04c2-4c72-897d-9f28f6027983">viewport</Link>. If the window has already been
          maximized, clicking the button again returns the window to its previous size. The button is a
          <Link target="9c6bfe16-d2dd-420b-b8ba-9d087bb9091c">standard button</Link>
          and therefore follows the same behaviours with respect to keyboard and mouse interaction.
        </Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>
          For a visible window, the maximize button is visible iff the following conditions hold:
        </Paragraph>
        <FormalItem title="Visibility Conditions">
          <ListUnordered>
            <Item>
              The window is decorated.
            </Item>
            <Item>
              The window's <Term type="variable">maximizeButtonVisibility</Term> attribute is set to
              <Term type="constant">VISIBILITY_VISIBLE</Term>.
            </Item>
          </ListUnordered>
        </FormalItem>
      </Subsection>
      <Subsection title="Events">
        <Paragraph>
          When a window is maximized, an event of type <Term type="type">SyWindowMaximized</Term> will be published.
          When a window is returned to normal size after having been maximized, an event of type
          <Term type="type">SyWindowUnmaximized</Term>
          will be published.
        </Paragraph>
      </Subsection>
    </Subsection>

    <Subsection title="Menu Button">
      <Subsection title="Description">
        <Paragraph>
          The <Term type="term">menu</Term> button, when clicked, opens a
          <Link target="ddd1079c-f636-4232-bebe-39672a140061">menu</Link>
          containing a list of actions that can otherwise be performed by the other standard window buttons.
          Hypothetically, the menu button is capable of subsuming the functionality of the other window buttons at the
          cost of having the user go through an intermediate menu to perform actions. The button is a
          <Link target="9c6bfe16-d2dd-420b-b8ba-9d087bb9091c">standard button</Link>
          and therefore follows the same behaviours with respect to keyboard and mouse interaction.
        </Paragraph>
        <FormalItem title="Menu Button Menu">
          <Image source="windowMenu.png"
                 width="640"
                 height="480">
            The window menu.
          </Image>
        </FormalItem>
        <Paragraph>
          For a visible window, the menu button is visible iff the following conditions hold:
        </Paragraph>
        <FormalItem title="Visibility Conditions">
          <ListUnordered>
            <Item>
              The window is decorated.
            </Item>
            <Item>
              The window's <Term type="variable">menuButtonVisibility</Term> attribute is set to
              <Term type="constant">VISIBILITY_VISIBLE</Term>.
            </Item>
          </ListUnordered>
        </FormalItem>
      </Subsection>
    </Subsection>

    <Subsection title="Resize Handles">
      <Subsection title="Overview">
        <Paragraph>
          <Term type="term">Resize handles</Term>
          are typically placed on the edges and corners of windows (this is dependent upon the
          <Link target="6aeefd35-8837-4503-99ee-3ccba984a49e">theme</Link>
          used), and allow the user to click and drag the handles to resize the windows.
        </Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>
          There are up to eight visible resize handles, each corresponding to the eight compass directions, and each
          implementing a specific kind of resize behaviour as detailed in the following sections. The behaviour of each
          handle is specified in terms of the user dragging the handles on the X and Y axes independently; the resulting
          effect on the window should be understood to be the sum of the effects along both axes.
        </Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>
          For a visible window, resize handle <Term type="variable">H</Term> is visible iff the following conditions
          hold:
        </Paragraph>
        <FormalItem title="Visibility Conditions">
          <ListUnordered>
            <Item>
              The window is decorated.
            </Item>
            <Item>
              The window's <Link target="6aeefd35-8837-4503-99ee-3ccba984a49e">theme</Link> specifies that
              <Term type="variable">H</Term>
              should be visible.
            </Item>
          </ListUnordered>
        </FormalItem>
        <Paragraph>
          Note that it is not technically a requirement for a theme to allow <Term type="term">any</Term> resize handle
          to be visible. However, making all handles invisible would be fairly user-hostile. Some applications may
          choose to design themes where only the
          <Link target="f1295748-ca82-46e1-b3fd-6704e1c64460">southeast</Link>
          resize handle is visible, as this matches the design of many traditional windowing systems.
        </Paragraph>
      </Subsection>
      <Subsection title="ResizeNW Handle">
        <Paragraph>
          Dragging the <Term type="term">northwest</Term> handle <Term type="variable">N</Term> units along the Y axis
          towards negative infinity will move the window <Term type="variable">N</Term> units towards negative infinity
          on the Y axis whilst also enlarging the window by <Term type="variable">N</Term> units on the Y axis.
        </Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>
          Dragging the <Term type="term">northwest</Term> handle <Term type="variable">M</Term> units along the X axis
          towards negative infinity will move the window <Term type="variable">M</Term> units towards negative infinity
          on the X axis whilst also enlarging the window by <Term type="variable">M</Term> units on the X axis.
        </Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>
          Dragging the <Term type="term">northwest</Term> handle <Term type="variable">P</Term> units along the Y axis
          towards positive infinity will move the window <Term type="variable">P</Term> units towards positive infinity
          on the Y axis whilst also shrinking the window by <Term type="variable">P</Term> units on the Y axis.
        </Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>
          Dragging the <Term type="term">northwest</Term> handle <Term type="variable">Q</Term> units along the X axis
          towards positive infinity will move the window <Term type="variable">Q</Term> units towards positive infinity
          on the X axis whilst also shrinking the window by <Term type="variable">Q</Term> units on the X axis.
        </Paragraph>
        <FormalItem title="Resize NW">
          <Image source="windowResizeNW.png"
                 width="582"
                 height="441">
            A window resizing northwest.
          </Image>
        </FormalItem>
      </Subsection>
      <Subsection title="ResizeN Handle">
        <Paragraph>
          Dragging the <Term type="term">north</Term> handle <Term type="variable">N</Term> units along the Y axis
          towards negative infinity will move the window <Term type="variable">N</Term> units towards negative infinity
          on the Y axis whilst also enlarging the window by <Term type="variable">N</Term> units on the Y axis.
        </Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>
          Dragging the <Term type="term">north</Term> handle <Term type="variable">M</Term> units along the Y axis
          towards positive infinity will move the window <Term type="variable">M</Term> units towards positive infinity
          on the Y axis whilst also shrinking the window by <Term type="variable">M</Term> units on the Y axis.
        </Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>
          Dragging the <Term type="term">north</Term> handle along the X axis has no effect on the window size or
          position.
        </Paragraph>
        <FormalItem title="Resize N">
          <Image source="windowResizeN.png"
                 width="582"
                 height="441">
            A window resizing north.
          </Image>
        </FormalItem>
      </Subsection>
      <Subsection title="ResizeNE Handle">
        <Paragraph>
          Dragging the <Term type="term">northeast</Term> handle <Term type="variable">N</Term> units along the Y axis
          towards negative infinity will move the window <Term type="variable">N</Term> units towards negative infinity
          on the Y axis whilst also enlarging the window by <Term type="variable">N</Term> units on the Y axis.
        </Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>
          Dragging the <Term type="term">northeast</Term> handle <Term type="variable">M</Term> units along the X axis
          towards negative infinity will shrink the window by <Term type="variable">M</Term> units on the X axis.
        </Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>
          Dragging the <Term type="term">northeast</Term> handle <Term type="variable">P</Term> units along the Y axis
          towards positive infinity will move the window <Term type="variable">P</Term> units towards positive infinity
          on the Y axis whilst also shrinking the window by <Term type="variable">P</Term> units on the Y axis.
        </Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>
          Dragging the <Term type="term">northeast</Term> handle <Term type="variable">Q</Term> units along the X axis
          towards positive infinity will enlarge the window by <Term type="variable">M</Term> units on the X axis.
        </Paragraph>
        <FormalItem title="Resize NE">
          <Image source="windowResizeNE.png"
                 width="582"
                 height="441">
            A window resizing northeast.
          </Image>
        </FormalItem>
      </Subsection>
      <Subsection title="ResizeE Handle">
        <Paragraph>
          Dragging the <Term type="term">east</Term> handle <Term type="variable">M</Term> units along the X axis
          towards negative infinity will shrink the window by <Term type="variable">M</Term> units on the X axis.
        </Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>
          Dragging the <Term type="term">northeast</Term> handle <Term type="variable">Q</Term> units along the X axis
          towards positive infinity will enlarge the window by <Term type="variable">M</Term> units on the X axis.
        </Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>
          Dragging the <Term type="term">east</Term> handle along the Y axis has no effect on the window size or
          position.
        </Paragraph>
        <FormalItem title="Resize E">
          <Image source="windowResizeE.png"
                 width="582"
                 height="441">
            A window resizing east.
          </Image>
        </FormalItem>
      </Subsection>
      <Subsection title="ResizeSE Handle"
                  id="f1295748-ca82-46e1-b3fd-6704e1c64460">
        <Paragraph>
          Dragging the <Term type="term">southeast</Term> handle <Term type="variable">N</Term> units along the Y axis
          towards negative infinity will shrink the window by <Term type="variable">N</Term> units on the Y axis.
        </Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>
          Dragging the <Term type="term">southeast</Term> handle <Term type="variable">M</Term> units along the X axis
          towards negative infinity will shrink the window by <Term type="variable">M</Term> units on the X axis.
        </Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>
          Dragging the <Term type="term">southeast</Term> handle <Term type="variable">P</Term> units along the Y axis
          towards positive infinity will enlarge the window by <Term type="variable">P</Term> units on the Y axis.
        </Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>
          Dragging the <Term type="term">southeast</Term> handle <Term type="variable">Q</Term> units along the X axis
          towards positive infinity will enlarge the window by <Term type="variable">M</Term> units on the X axis.
        </Paragraph>
        <FormalItem title="Resize SE">
          <Image source="windowResizeSE.png"
                 width="582"
                 height="441">
            A window resizing southeast.
          </Image>
        </FormalItem>
      </Subsection>
      <Subsection title="ResizeS Handle">
        <Paragraph>
          Dragging the <Term type="term">south</Term> handle <Term type="variable">N</Term> units along the Y axis
          towards negative infinity will shrink the window by <Term type="variable">N</Term> units on the Y axis.
        </Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>
          Dragging the <Term type="term">south</Term> handle <Term type="variable">P</Term> units along the Y axis
          towards positive infinity will enlarge the window by <Term type="variable">P</Term> units on the Y axis.
        </Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>
          Dragging the <Term type="term">south</Term> handle along the X axis has no effect on the window size or
          position.
        </Paragraph>
        <FormalItem title="Resize S">
          <Image source="windowResizeS.png"
                 width="582"
                 height="441">
            A window resizing south.
          </Image>
        </FormalItem>
      </Subsection>
      <Subsection title="ResizeSW Handle">
        <Paragraph>
          Dragging the <Term type="term">southwest</Term> handle <Term type="variable">N</Term> units along the Y axis
          towards negative infinity will shrink the window by <Term type="variable">N</Term> units on the Y axis.
        </Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>
          Dragging the <Term type="term">southwest</Term> handle <Term type="variable">M</Term> units along the X axis
          towards negative infinity will move the window <Term type="variable">M</Term> units towards negative infinity
          on the X axis whilst also enlarging the window by <Term type="variable">M</Term> units on the X axis.
        </Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>
          Dragging the <Term type="term">southwest</Term> handle <Term type="variable">P</Term> units along the Y axis
          towards positive infinity will enlarge the window by <Term type="variable">P</Term> units on the Y axis.
        </Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>
          Dragging the <Term type="term">southwest</Term> handle <Term type="variable">Q</Term> units along the X axis
          towards positive infinity will move the window <Term type="variable">Q</Term> units towards positive infinity
          on the X axis whilst also shrinking the window by <Term type="variable">Q</Term> units on the X axis.
        </Paragraph>
        <FormalItem title="Resize SW">
          <Image source="windowResizeSW.png"
                 width="582"
                 height="441">
            A window resizing southwest.
          </Image>
        </FormalItem>
      </Subsection>
      <Subsection title="ResizeW Handle">
        <Paragraph>
          Dragging the <Term type="term">west</Term> handle <Term type="variable">M</Term> units along the X axis
          towards negative infinity will move the window <Term type="variable">M</Term> units towards negative infinity
          on the X axis whilst also enlarging the window by <Term type="variable">M</Term> units on the X axis.
        </Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>
          Dragging the <Term type="term">west</Term> handle <Term type="variable">Q</Term> units along the X axis
          towards positive infinity will move the window <Term type="variable">Q</Term> units towards positive infinity
          on the X axis whilst also shrinking the window by <Term type="variable">Q</Term> units on the X axis.
        </Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>
          Dragging the <Term type="term">west</Term> handle along the Y axis has no effect on the window size or
          position.
        </Paragraph>
        <FormalItem title="Resize W">
          <Image source="windowResizeW.png"
                 width="582"
                 height="441">
            A window resizing west.
          </Image>
        </FormalItem>
      </Subsection>
    </Subsection>

    <Subsection title="Title Bar">
      <Paragraph>
        The <Term type="term">title bar</Term> displays the contents of the window's
        <Term type="variable">title</Term>
        attribute, and allows the user to move the window by dragging with the mouse.
      </Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>
        Dragging the
        <Term type="term">title bar</Term>
        <Term type="variable">M</Term>
        units along the X axis will move the window <Term type="variable">M</Term> units along the X axis.
      </Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>
        Dragging the
        <Term type="term">title bar</Term>
        <Term type="variable">N</Term>
        units along the Y axis will move the window <Term type="variable">N</Term> units along the Y axis.
      </Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>
        For a visible window, the title bar is visible iff the following conditions hold:
      </Paragraph>
      <FormalItem title="Visibility">
        <ListUnordered>
          <Item>
            The window is decorated.
          </Item>
        </ListUnordered>
      </FormalItem>
    </Subsection>

    <Subsection title="Content Area">
      <Paragraph>
        The <Term type="term">content area</Term> is the rectangular region dedicated to the actual
        <Term type="term">content</Term>
        of the window; it is the component that serves as the parent component of components added to the window for
        display. The content area itself is effectively invisible; themes should not render the content area as being
        any particular colour or shape. The content area does not consume
        any <Link target="bcc3c7a6-df1c-4dc8-8263-2364630db64a">events</Link>.
      </Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>
        For a visible window, the content area is always visible.
      </Paragraph>
    </Subsection>
  </Section>

</Section>
